Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to
be learning about how to dilute solutions
and go through many different examples and
to explain exactly what it is that you're
going to be using when you're in your
general chemistry or introductory biology
courses, when you have to do dilutions,
which is a very common skill that you'll
need as a scientist or as a student.
So with this formula, what
it's all about is we're going
to be using the formula above.
Which is M1V1=M2V2.
So when, what is that all about?
So what are we talking about
when it comes to dilutions?
So the easiest way to think
about it is, let's say I wanted
to make, let's say a solution.
Let's say I wanted to make Kool-Aid or
a lemonade or iced tea or something.
And when you make it originally, so on
the very far left and you drink it and you
realize like, oh, that is way too sweet.
What do you do, right?
If something is too sweet, too
salty, how do you change it?
Well, usually the first thing
you do is you dilute it, right?
You add a little bit of water.
So when you do that, so let's say if
I started to over here on the far left
and I add a little bit of water and
I keep adding water, one thing you'll
notice is the color is going to change.
It's gonna get lighter
and lighter and lighter.
Why is that happening?
Well, because the concentration Of the,
of the juice that's in that powder is
getting less and less and less, meaning
you're not going to taste it as much.
It's being diluted.
So it's becoming less sweet.
And that's the whole idea of dilution.
We're making our solutions less sweet
in a way or less moles in our solution.
So this is what we're going to be
exploring when we're looking at this.
So let's take a look and this
is going to be a skill that
you're going to use in the lab.
That's very common.
So let's try to figure out how to do
different calculations for it and how
to utilize it for your chemistry course.
So the first thing is when we're
looking at M1V1=M2V2 is that as
you may have realized, this is a
relationship between concentration.
and volume.
So why M instead of maybe another letter?
M is usually representing of molarity,
meaning that's usually the most common
concentration that's used in chem.
However, you might have also seen
the version of the formula above,
which is C1V1 is equal to C2V2.
Both formulas are identical because
they are an inverse relationship.
Meaning that as volume goes
up, concentration goes down.
So if you like one version or the other,
they'll both work the same as long as
you're using your concentration as C or M.
So what I'm trying to get to is
that this formula can be used for
molarity, for percents, for molality.
It can be used for any of the
concentrations as long as the
units are matching on both sides.
So meaning molarity has to cancel
molarity, millimoles have to
cancel millimoles, liters have to
cancel liters, everything needs
to match on the left and right.
So, let's take a look at some examples
of how exactly we can use this for
our skills so that we can do the
best that we can in our account.
1.
3 molar solution needs to have
a final concentration of 0.
0400 molarity.
What the heck does that even mean?
So when we're doing this, being that, as
you remember, the formula was M1V1=M2V2.
So the first thing I would recommend
doing is, with these, is stay organized.
It's talking about making a new solution.
So you see that there's change involved.
So when you're, it's talking
about this, of making a new
solution, it's the same chemicals.
It's talking about diluting it.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to write out M1.
V one, M two, V two, and all that
separately, and we're gonna see
is which pieces were we given?
So at the very beginning of
the prom, it says we have 10
milliliters of a 1.30 molar solution.
So that's on the second line here.
Now what those represent are those
two terms are together, meaning
they're part of the same solution.
So we're going to label that as
solution one, um, and they are together.
It doesn't matter if they're, if
they're one or two, as long as they go
together, that's the most important part.
So the molarity, you
have 10 milliliters of 1.
30 molar.
And it wants to know what the final volume
is, so we'll put a question mark by that.
And it says that the,
the concentration is 0.
0400 molarity.
Okay, looks good.
So now what we're going to do is we're
going to plug all this into our equation.
We want V2, so we'll move things around
a little bit and get V2 by itself.
So divide M2 by both sides.
So now what we will have is we'll take 1.
30 molar times that by 10 milliliters,
and then we're going to divide that by 0.
0400 molarity.
And now the one thing you're going
to notice is you'll see that the
molarity, being that these are the
same units, they're going to cancel
each other out, which is really
important to kind of realize here.
that both these two cancel.
Now what this is going to leave
you is only with milliliters,
so we're going to do 1.
3 times 10, and then we're
going to divide that by 0.
05.
And we get 325 milliliters of our
solution here, and this will be your final
answer for your first dilution problem.
So not too bad, right?
So and this is kind of the general
idea of how we put all these together.
Let's take a look at another
problem of working with dilutions.
You have 0.
600 molar NaCl stock solution.
You need to make 500 of
a 20 millimolar dilution.
What volumes do you add?
So sometimes you might be told
when you walk into a lab is
that you need to make this.
And you're like, what, what
do you mean I need to do that?
It's not always given to you, which is
sometimes really scary and especially
the first time you have to do it.
So once again, what we're going
to do is we're going to write
down everything that we had.
So it says you have a 0.
600 molar NaCl solution.
So let's write down that first thing.
So that's M1.
So we got 0.
600 molar.
Now it's, and that's referred
to as a stock solution.
What does that mean?
So a stock solution refers to
the most concentrated solution
that you have available.
Meaning it's like what's available
in the stock room or the prep room.
So it's what you have on hand.
So if it's your stock solution, you
can't go any more concentrated than that.
You can only go down.
So you can dilute, you can't go upwards.
So remember that for later.
So you need to make 500 milliliters
of a 20 millimolar solution.
So we actually don't know what
volume one is because it's
asking us what we're adding.
But we do know V2, which is 500 mLs,
and we know M2, which is 20 millimoles.
All right, so what else
is kind of a problem here?
Well, notice how the
units don't quite match.
So we have 20 millimoles here.
And then we have 600 molar up here.
So what we need to do is, is essentially
convert this guy on the bottom to molar.
So we'll divide this number
by 1000, we'll get 0.
0200 molarity.
Now we can plug all this into our formula.
So when we are to do this.
We are going to have V1 is
equal to m2 V2 divided by m1.
So we'll take, uh, 0.
0200 times that by 500.
And it's, as you kind of notice how
important it was to make sure the
units match, because if they don't,
then you, you're not going to be,
you're not going to get a right answer.
So we'll see that we
have, molar on bottom.
The two terms cancel out, which is great.
And what that's going
to leave us with is 16.
7 milliliters of solution is required.
So now what this refers to is, is this
exactly how you make the solution?
It's not.
This is only part of it.
So if you were to do this and you
were how, what volume do you need?
I didn't specify anything.
So sometimes you need
to make the whole thing.
So this refers to in here is 16.
7 milliliters of your stock solution.
which is what you will
add first to your flask.
Now, being that it's talking about
making a 500 mL solution, you
would dilute this volume, the 16.
7 mL here, with DI water.
So what you would do is you'd take your
little DI water bottle, you would fill
up the vol flask here, with the rest
of it with water up to the line on your
volumetric flask to get 500 milliliters.
So essentially to make your solution is
you would fill the rest with DI water.
Now, could you just calculate
it and you'd get like 483.
3 or whatever number it is?
Yeah, you would, but you got to keep
in mind is you want to fill it to the
glassware because it's calibrated.
So we fill the rest with the
eye water, is the right answer.
Let's take a look at another problem.
You need to make 4 liters of a 0.
900 percent saline solution.
You check the storeroom, and you find 0.
450 percent and a 20
percent saline solution.
What do you use to make this?
And what volume of that solute do you
need to add to make your solution?
Okay, so this is a tough one.
Let's take a look.
So, what it says is, let's
write everything down.
So, our volume 2 is, we need a, we need to
make 4 liters with a concentration of 0.
900%.
And from that, we are trying to figure
out what our original volume is, and
we have a couple options for volume,
for the molarity here, which is pretty
common in terms of a chemistry lab.
What do you use to make this?
Now, the thing is you need to dilute
the stock solution to do this.
So if we were to kind of put these
over here, which one can you dilute?
Can you dilute 0.
450 percent to 0.
9 or can you dilute 20 percent to 0.
9?
Which one is making it less sweet as
per se or less salty in this case?
Which one is that?
Well, if you think about it,
well, that is going to be the 20%.
Because it's more concentrated,
you need to go down.
You cannot go up.
So we will use a 20 percent here,
and we're going to set it up just
like how we did the last problem.
So being that they're percents, the beauty
of this is that they'll cancel each other
out when we are trying to solve this.
So we'll have 0.
9 percent times 4, divide that by
20%, and you can see here is that
the percents will cancel, being
that they're made of the same thing.
So what this will give you is 0.
180 liters is what's required to make
this, which I kind of put that in
normal speak, there's nothing that
measures just liters in the lab.
This would be about 180 milliliters is
how much you would use of your solute.
So if you were to try to do the
solvent part, you would fill it
up to four liters of your vessel.
To make the rest of the solution.
Okay, so this has been all my examples
and dilutions So I try to go through
some different examples of real real
practical examples for how to do this
I hope that this helped you understand
it a little bit more for something
that you will have to do in the lab
If you need any help, feel free to
comment below message me Hit the like
button subscribe if you haven't before
and I hope to see you back for future
videos Thank you so much for listening.
I hope you have a wonderful day.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now